It was well past midnight this past July and the round-the-clock Arctic sun was shining on Mercy Bay.
刚刚过去的七月里，时间早已过了午夜，北极昼夜不落的太阳照耀着慈悲湾。
Exhausted Parks Canada archaeologist Ryan Harris was experiencing a rare moment of rest on the rocky beach, looking out over the bay’s dark, ice-studded water.
加拿大公园管理局的考古学家瑞安·哈里斯已经筋疲力尽，此刻正在满是岩石的海滩上享受难得的片刻休息，眺望着海湾里浮冰点点的幽暗海水。
Around him, a dozen red-and-yellow tents lined the shoreline—the only signs of life.
他四周的海岸线上排列着十二顶红黄相间的帐篷——这是那里仅有的生命迹象。
Every day for the previous two weeks, work had started by mid-morning and continued nonstop for 16 hours.
此前两周，每天的工作最晚上午十点左右就开始，一刻不停地持续16个小时。
Night and day had little relevance in the murky, near-freezing waters.
在浑浊而接近冰点的海水里，是白天还是黑夜几乎无关紧要。
Along with Parks Canada’s chief of underwater archaeology, Marc-Andre Bernier, Harris has overseen more than 100 dives at this remote inlet of Banks Island in Aulavik National Park, exploring the wreck of HMS Investigator, a British vessel that has sat on the bottom of the bay for more than 150 years.
哈里斯与加拿大公园管理局水下考古负责人马克-安德烈·贝尼耶一起，在班克斯岛奥拉维克国家公园内这处偏远的小海湾已主持了100多次潜水，考察英国皇家海军“调查者”号的残骸；这艘英国船只已在湾底躺了150多年。
Harris and a small team of archaeologists had discovered Investigator in 2010 and returned in 2011 with a larger team to dive, study, and document the wreck, which holds a critical place in the history of Arctic exploration.
哈里斯和一支由考古学家组成的小团队于2010年发现了“调查者”号，2011年又带着一支更大的团队重返此地，潜水考察、研究并记录这艘沉船——它在北极探险史上占有至关重要的地位。
Twenty-five feet below the surface, Investigator sits upright, intact, and remarkably well preserved.
在水面以下25英尺处，“调查者”号直立着，完整无损，保存得出奇完好。
Silt covers everything below the main deck, entombing the officers’ cabins, the ship’s galley, and a full library.
淤泥覆盖了主甲板以下的一切，把军官舱室、船上的厨房和一间藏书齐全的图书室都掩埋在下面。
The archaeologists had intended to leave the wreck and its artifacts where they had lain since the polar ship was abandoned, trapped in ice, on June 3, 1853.
考古学家原本打算让沉船及其文物留在原处——自1853年6月3日这艘极地船只被困冰中、遭到弃置以来，它们就一直躺在那里。
Artifact recovery was not part of their original plan, but that plan changed after their first few dives.
打捞文物本不在他们原定的计划之内，但最初几次潜水之后，这个计划就改变了。
The team was instantly surprised by the number of artifacts they saw—muskets, shoes, and hunks of copper sheathing rested on Investigator’s upper deck, dangled off the hull, or lay haphazardly on the sediment.
团队立刻对眼前文物的数量感到吃惊——火枪、鞋子和大块大块的铜护层，有的搁在“调查者”号的上甲板上，有的从船体上垂挂下来，有的杂乱地躺在沉积物上。
Leaving these artifacts behind in Mercy Bay would have made them vulnerable to the icebergs that regularly scour the bay’s floor, including the ones the six-man dive team had been dodging since their arrival.
如果当初把这些文物留在慈悲湾，它们就会很容易遭到冰山破坏；这些冰山经常刮擦湾底，其中就包括六人潜水队自抵达以来一直在躲避的那些。
Each piece fished from the water was a clue to life at sea aboard a ship during a period of British fervor for Arctic exploration.
从水中打捞出的每一件物品，都为了解英国北极探险热潮时期船上的海上生活提供了一条线索。
The captain of Investigator, Robert McClure, was originally sent to find and rescue two ships, HMS Erebus and HMS Terror, that Sir John Franklin had led into the Arctic in 1845 to discover the long-sought Northwest Passage connecting the Atlantic and Pacific oceans.
“调查者”号的船长罗伯特·麦克卢尔最初奉命去寻找并营救两艘船，即英国皇家海军“幽冥”号和“惊恐”号；1845年，约翰·富兰克林爵士率领这两艘船驶入北极，旨在发现人们寻觅已久、连接大西洋和太平洋的西北航道。
Investigator’s voyage ended, without sight or word of Franklin’s ships or crew, when it was set upon by ice in Mercy Bay.
“调查者”号在慈悲湾遭到冰层围攻，航程就此结束，始终没有见到富兰克林的船只或船员，也没有得到他们的任何消息。
After 39 months at sea, the listing ship sat, slowly being crushed on all sides, for three frigid years—with no Inuit encounters, no British search parties, and no relief.
在海上度过39个月后，这艘倾斜的船在严寒中一停就是三年，四面八方都在慢慢挤压它——其间没有遇到因纽特人，没有英国搜救队前来，也没有任何救援。
For much of that time, McClure and his crew of 60 were desperate and under constant threat of starvation, until a surprising rescue in the spring of 1853.
在那段时间的大部分时候，麦克卢尔和他的60名船员都陷于绝望，时刻面临饿死的威胁，直到1853年春天才出人意料地获救。
Fifty-five men survived the ordeal.
55人从这场磨难中幸存了下来。
In July 2010, after months of study to pinpoint Investigator’s resting place, the actual discovery of the wreck took just a few minutes.
为精确定位“调查者”号的长眠之处，研究工作持续了数月；而2010年7月，真正发现这艘沉船只用了短短几分钟。
Harris was in the bay in an inflatable boat testing sonar equipment when the wreck came into range.
当时，哈里斯正在海湾里乘着一艘充气艇测试声呐设备，沉船就在这时进入了探测范围。
The four hours of video gathered on that trip showed that the ship was, in essence, frozen in time, protected by the cold water and opaque, light-blocking ice cover.
那次考察拍摄的4个小时视频显示，这艘船实际上被定格在了时光里，受到寒冷海水以及不透明、能遮挡光线的冰盖保护。
It would be a year before they could return with cold-water diving equipment to have a closer, more detailed look.
他们要过一年才能带着冷水潜水装备重返此地，更近、更仔细地察看沉船。
Over that year, the Parks Canada team pored over photographs and examined glowing gold ultrasound images that showed timber from the wreck scattered across the upper deck like matchsticks.
在那一年里，加拿大公园管理局的团队仔细研究了照片，还查看了一张张闪着金光的超声波图像；图像显示，沉船上的木材像火柴棍一样散落在上甲板各处。
They sought and received the blessing for a more intensive exploration of the wreck site from the 136 residents of Sachs Harbour, an Inuvialuit (Inuit from the western Arctic) community on the southwestern tip of Banks Island, the closest permanent community, some 125 miles away.
他们请求萨克斯港的136位居民准许他们更深入地考察沉船地点，并得到了同意；萨克斯港是因纽维阿卢伊特人（北极西部的因纽特人）的一个社区，位于班克斯岛西南端，是离沉船最近的永久性社区，相距约125英里。
In addition to the underwater work to document the wreck, archaeologist Henry Cary led a land-based survey and excavation team of Inuvialuit archaeologists, conservation officers, and park staff.
除了记录沉船的水下工作外，考古学家亨利·卡里还带领一支陆上勘测与发掘队，队员包括因纽维阿卢伊特考古学家、资源保护官员和公园工作人员。
It fell upon Cary to shuttle the 8,820 pounds of equipment up to the 74th parallel, including tents, a three-week supply of food, two boats, diving gear, compressors, recording equipment, surveying tools, and 20 barrels for collecting fresh drinking water.
把这8820磅装备分趟运到北纬74度线的任务落在了卡里身上，这些装备包括帐篷、够吃三周的食物、两艘船、潜水装备、压缩机、录制设备、勘测工具，以及20个用来收集饮用淡水的桶。
The archaeologists came prepared for delays, nasty weather, and polar bears—but they weren’t prepared for the number of artifacts that needed recovery.
考古学家们来时已为延误、恶劣天气和北极熊做好了准备，但对需要打捞的文物数量，他们却没有做好准备。
Harris, Bernier, Cary, and their crews had packed cameras, lasers, and measuring tapes to document the sites but fewer items to help them retrieve, excavate, or transfer artifacts.
哈里斯、贝尼耶、卡里和他们的队员打包带来了相机、激光仪和卷尺，用来记录这些地点，而帮助他们取回、发掘或转移文物的物品则带得少一些。
Recovering the wreck’s finds quickly used up their small toolkit for stabilizing artifacts: foam padding, tongue depressors, and gauze bandages.
打捞沉船中的出水文物，很快就用光了他们那个用来稳固文物的小工具包：泡沫衬垫、压舌板和纱布绷带。
“We had not really envisioned the number of artifacts that were visible and exposed on the deck.
“我们事先并没有真正预料到，甲板上看得见、暴露在外的文物会有这么多。
So, basically, we had to improvise,” says Bernier.
所以，说白了，我们只能临时想办法。”贝尼耶说。
Someone ripped the lid of a large black storage case off its hinges to use as a cradle to lift a bent and corroded musket from the frigid waters.
有人把一个黑色大储物箱的盖子从铰链上扯了下来，当作托架，用它把一支弯曲锈蚀的火枪从冰冷刺骨的海水中托了上来。
A large food cooler was loaded with a shredded, twisted, oxidized sample of the copper sheathing used by the British navy to reinforce their Arctic fleet for contact with icebergs.
一个大号食品冷藏箱里装上了一块破碎、扭曲、氧化的铜护层样本；英国海军曾用这种铜护层加固其北极舰队，以抵御与冰山的碰撞。
To protect a fragile rectangle of encrusted felt—a novel addition to Investigator that was intended to keep the ship watertight—Harris fashioned a cover out of absorbent chamois, ripped up an old black T-shirt to place underneath it, and sandwiched the artifact between floorboards taken from the boat that had shuttled them between land and the wreck.
为了保护一块易碎的、结了硬壳的长方形毛毡（这是“调查者”号上新颖的加装物，用来让船身保持水密），哈里斯用吸水的鹿皮做了一个罩子，撕开一件旧的黑色T恤垫在下面，再用从小船上拆下的底板把这件文物夹在中间；那艘小船此前一直载着他们往返于陆地和沉船之间。
The artifacts then made a more than 4,000-mile journey, by helicopter and commercial airliner, to the Parks Canada conservation lab in Ottawa, where they are being conserved and studied today.
随后，这些文物搭乘直升机和民航客机，经过4000多英里的旅程，运抵位于渥太华的加拿大公园管理局文物保护实验室，如今正在那里接受保护处理和研究。